Finding Aid for A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture + Urban Planning Records 1876-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Dean's Administrative Files 1957-2008
  - Robert C. Metcalf
    - 1967-1988
      Although the majority of the 1967-1988 files (received in the 1993 accession) date from the deanship of Robert C. Metcalf, there are also materials from the tenure of Dean Reginald F. Malcomson (1964-1974). The file is arranged alphabetically by topic, and documents activities, goals and objectives, research, and faculty life of the college, particularly relating to Architecture. Informative background is provided in the essay "History of Architecture and Design, 1952-1974." The essay was later edited by Ferol Brinkman and published in the University of Michigan, An Encyclopedic Survey, Volume V (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan, 1977).
      Activities occurring within the college are best documented in the "Annual Report Files" and the "Letter From the Dean" file found under the heading "Alumni." The "Annual Report Files" include drafts of yearly reports to the university president, in addition to background materials collected for preparation of the report. Background materials consist of news releases (announcing guest speakers, award recipients and special events), inter-office memos and clippings. The "Letter From the Dean" is an annual letter sent to the alumni highlighting major events and activities, memorial funds, financial gifts, and enrollment figures. There is not a complete run of these letters. The "Vice President for Academic Affairs Correspondence," which is primarily outgoing, provides information on budgets, academic and appointment policies, faculty listings and program development.
      Strategic plans of action, and statements of goals and objectives can be found under "Annual Report Files," "Educational Development Plan," and "Futures." The latter is found under the heading "Committees." Research conducted in the college is documented under several different headings: "Architecture Research Laboratory/Architecture & Planning Research Laboratory," "Research," "Student Research Review," and "Funding Proposals." Files under these headings contain student and faculty research proposals and funded project listings that include sponsorship and funding amount. The researcher should also inspect the contents of the "Center for Architecture and Planning Studies" folder. There is information on the unsuccessful attempt to establish a research center that would have served as an advanced educational and consultative organization. The center would have combined research activities at the university with professional services of non-university architects to solve problems dealing with environmental planning and design. The researcher interested in faculty members of the college will find the "Promotions" files especially illuminating. For every Board of Regents approved faculty promotion, there is a profile containing academic and professional experience, publications, academic degrees and university appointments.
      - Adult Continuing Education 1967-1976 (Box 17)
      - Alumni
        - Deceased
          - Lenhouts, Lillian Scott 1982-1990 (Box 17)
          - Malbin, Lydia Kahn Winston,1989 (Box 17)
          - Oberdick, Will 1982 (Box 17)
          - Robinson, Richard M. 1988 (Box 17)
          - Whitman, Bertha Yerex 1974-1985 (Box 17)
        - Letter From the Dean 1969-1986 (summary of year activities) (Box 17)
        - Luncheon 1968, 1975, 1977 (Box 17)
      - Annual Report Files (background materials and drafts)
        - 1961-1968 (Box 17)
        - 1969-1972 (Box 17)
        - 1973 (Box 17)
        - 1974 (Box 17)
        - 1975 (Box 17)
        - 1976 (Box 17)
        - 1977 (Box 17)
        - 1978 (Box 17)
        - 1979 (Box 17)
        - 1980 (Box 17)
        - 1981 (Box 17)
        - 1982 (Box 17)
        - 1983 (Box 17)
        - 1984 (Box 17)
        - 1985 (Box 17)
        - 1986 (Box 17)
      - American Institute of Architects (AIA)
        - Correspondence 1968-1981 (Box 17)
        - School Medal and Book Award 1965-1967 (Box 17)
        - University of Michigan Branch of Detroit Chapter 1940-1951 (minute book) (Box 17)
      - Architecture Course/Curriculum Evaluation System (ACCESS) 1976-1978 (Box 17)
      - Architecture Research Laboratory/Architecture & Planning Research Laboratory
        - General 1972-1982 (Box 17)
        - Funded Research 1970-1986 (Box 17)
      - Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture (ACSA)
        - East Central Regional Meeting
          - General
            - 1975 (Box 17)
            - 1979 (Box 17)
            - 1982 (Box 17)
          - Correspondence 1968-1981 (Box 17)
      - ACSA/AIA Teachers Seminar 1962-1980 (Box 17)
      - Capital Campaign 1974-1979 (Box 17)
      - Centennial Weekend 1976 (Box 17)
      - Center for Architecture and Planning Studies 1981-1982 (Box 17)
      - Civil Defense, Office of 1960-1967 (Box 17)
      - Committees
        - College of Architecture and Design Review 1974 (report) (Box 17)
        - College Executive
          - Minutes 1961-1986 (Box 17)
          - Correspondence 1967-1981 (Box 17)
        - Deanship Search Committee
          - 1975 (Box 17)
          - 1980 (Box 17)
        - Environmental Studies, College Committee on 1970 (Box 18)
        - Futures 1984-1985 (Box 18)
          (self study and plan for the future)
        - GEO Advisory 1975-1982 (Box 18)
        - Program Evaluation 1972, 1974 (Box 18)
        - Student Research Review 1972-1973 (Box 18)
        - Student/Faculty 1958-1966 (includes minutes) (Box 18)
      - Computers in Architectural Education Conference 1969 (Box 18)
      - Comprehensive Development Plans 1979 (Box 18)
      - Continuing Education 1968 (Box 18)
      - Correspondence 1968-1986 (Box 18)
      - Detroit Public Schools Building Program 1978 (Box 18)
      - Dual Degree (Architecture & Urban Planning) 1975-1981 (Box 18)
      - Educational Development Plan 1976 (Box 18)
      - Emery M. Suhrbier Scholarship 1970-1971 (Box 18)
      - Faculty
        - Luncheon Seminars 1981-1982 (Box 18)
        - Retreat 1980 (Box 18)
        - Specialty Listing 1985 (Box 18)
      - Fleming, Robben 1968-1975 (correspondence) (Box 18)
      - Funding Proposals 1971-1977 (Box 18)
      - Historic Preservation 1971-1978 (Box 18)
      - Historical Notes 1974 (Box 18)
      - History of Architecture and Design, 1952-1974, 1976 (Box 18)
      - Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1973-1981 (Box 18)
        (CAUP candidates for executive and divisional boards)
      - Institute for Environmental Quality 1970-1981 (Box 18)
      - Master of Science Degree Proposal 1986 (Box 18)
      - National Architectural Accrediting Board 1981-1985 (Box 18)
      - News Releases 1960-1971 (Box 18)
      - Phonathon 1985 (Box 18)
      - Professional Exposure Program 1974-1976 (Box 18)
      - Promotion and Tenure Procedures 1966, 1975 (Box 18)
      - Promotions
        - 1964-1965 (Box 18)
        - 1965-1966 (Box 18)
        - 1966-1967 (Box 18)
        - 1967-1968 (Box 18)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 18)
        - 1969-1970 (Box 18)
        - 1970-1971 (Box 18)
        - 1970-1971 (Box 18)
        - 1972-1973 (Box 18)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 18)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 18)
        - 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 22)
        - 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Research
        - Annual Summary Activity 1970-1973 (Box 18)
        - An Evaluation 1980 (Box 18)
        - Sponsored 1968-1981 (Box 19)
        - Student Projects 1973 (Box 19)
      - Sabbatical Leave Reports 1973-1982 (Box 19)
      - Scholarships 1965 (Box 19)
      - School of Natural Resources 1978-1984 (collaborative efforts) (Box 19)
      - Sesquicentennial Celebration 1965-1967 (Box 19)
      - Solar Design Education Seminar 1978 (Box 19)
      - Solar Energy Utilization Conference 1976 (Box 19)
      - Teaching Position Advertisements
        - 1972-1986 (Box 19)
      - Tuskegee Institute Exchange 1969-1970 (Box 19)
      - Urban Planning, Department of (establishment of) 1968 (Box 19)
      - Vice President for Academic Affairs (Correspondence)
        - 1965-1968 (Smith, Allan F.) (Box 19)
        - 1974-1977 (Rhodes, Frank H. T.) (Box 19)
        - 1977-1980 (Shapiro, Harold) (Box 19)
        - 1980-1986 (Frye, Billy E.) (Box 19)
    - 1969-1997
      The Metcalf, 1969-1994 files will be particularly valued for the collection of speeches and presentations, which run from 1969 to 1994. Research files are equally illuminating when considering directions undertaken during Metcalf's leadership.
      - Articles and Reference
        - Architectural Education, 2 folders (Box 33)
        - General (Box 33)
      - Beckley, Robert 1986-1987 (Box 34)
      - Continuing Education 1984-1986 (Box 34)
      - Dean's Notes / Report to the Faculty 1966-1974 (Box 34)
      - Dean Search 1985 (Box 22)
      - Eighty Percent Appointments 1966-1987 (Box 34)
      - GROW and the UM Design Team 1980 (Box 34)
        (includes photographs)
      - Historica Critica 1987 (Box 34)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 34)
      - Research
        - General 1984 (Box 34)
        - Development 1984-1985 (Box 34)
        - Proposed Center for Architectural Planning and Development 1982 (Box 34)
        - Swedish American Seminar 1985 (Box 34)
        - Research Volume 1980-1981 (Box 34)
      - Speeches, Presentations 1969-1994 (Box 34)
      - Surveys and Responses 1977-1992, 2 folders (Box 34)
      - Wallenberg
        - Lecture 1991 (Box 34)
        - Memorial Dedication 1995 (Box 34)
  - Robert M. Beckley
    Dean Robert Beckley's administrative files are particularly rich for documentation of his interest in campus planning, captured, for example, in 1989 transcripts and audiotapes of the A. Alfred Taubman Symposium on Campus Planning. The forum, charged with addressing pressing issues facing campus growth, engaged participants in thinking creatively about development needs. Files also include material from a lecture and panel discussion on the future of design education that marked the Beckley inauguration, a solid run of his speeches and presentations from 1988 to 1993, and a collection of cards and letters he received upon retirement.
    - 1986-1996
      - Class of 1950 1990 (Box 34)
      - Class of 1966 1991 (Box 34)
      - Faculty Profiles 1988-1989 (Box 34)
      - Florence Trip 1996 (Box 34)
      - Inaugural Lecture 1986-1987 (Box 34)
      - Presentations 1988-1993 (Box 34)
      - Research 1979-1992, 2 folders (Box 35)
      - Retirement Cards and Letters 1996-1997 (Box 35)
      - Reunions, Doctoral 1990 (Box 35)
      - Shelter Women Conference 1992 (Box 35)
      - Taubman Symposium (Symposium on Campus Planning) 1989
        - Transcript, 1 folders (Box 35)
        - Audio tapes, 8 audiocassettes (Box 35)
  - 1982-2000
    - Career Conference 1994-1995 (Box 51)
    - Carter, Brian 1996-1998 (Box 51)
    - Chair Appointment 1996-1997 (Box 51)
    - Curriculum
      - Criteria for Tenure and Promotion, Draft 1986 (Box 51)
      - Faculty Fellowships 1994 (Box 51)
      - General 1994 (Box 51)
      - Other Courses 1982 (Box 51)
      - Undergrad Studies 1994 (Box 51)
    - Distinguished Dissertations 1993-1996 (Box 51)
    - Evaluations, Course
      - 1982-1984, 4 folders (Box 51)
      - 1987 (Box 51)
      - 1991 (Box 51)
      - General 1982-1993 (scattered) (Box 51)
    - Library
      - Program 1984 (Box 51)
      - Committee 1993-1996 (Box 51)
      - Current and Future State 1986 (Box 51)
      - Renovations 1993 (Box 51)
    - Miscellaneous 1988-1993 (Box 52)
    - Monograph Mailing, Post Professional and Doctorate Education 1991 (Box 52)
    - Personnel 1988-1994 (Box 55)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2024 ]
    - Policies 1978-1987 (Box 52)
    - Policy Manual 1984-1992 (Box 52)
    - Practice Management Associates 1988-1993 (Box 52)
    - Presidential Initiative Fund 1994 (Box 52)
    - Research Incentive Program 1987-1992 (Box 52)
    - Russian Delegation 1999 (Box 52)
    - Searches, Harvey, David 2000, 2 folders (Box 55)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2030 ]
    - Space Committee 1990-1995, 2 folders (Box 52)
    - Space and Security 1995 (Box 52)
    - Staffing 1995-1996 (Box 55)
    - Strategic Planning Report 1988 (Box 52)
    - Student Recruitment 1994 (Box 52)
    - Symposium on Doctoral Education 1988 (Box 52)
    - Teaching Excellence Award 1991 (Box 52)
    - UM TV Space 1993-1994 (Box 52)
  - Douglas S. Kelbaugh 1993-2008
    The Kelbaugh subseries of the Dean's Administrative Files, 1993-2008 (bulk 1998-2008) (3 linear feet and 1 oversize box) continues the series from previous accessions. The records in this series primarily originate from Douglas S. Kelbaugh's tenure as dean, but also include files from Dean Robert M. Beckley, and Interim Dean James Snyder's tenures. Included in the series are files on each of the annual charrettes hosted by TCAUP from 1999 to 2008. The charrettes, which are collaborative design planning sessions, were initiated by Dean Kelbaugh as an effort on the part of the University and TCAUP to help revitalize Detroit. Each year the charrettes focused on a different section of Detroit. The charrettes were held at the UM Detroit Center, which is also well-documented in this series. In addition to hosting the charrettes TCAUP is also involved in other programs at the Detroit Center, and, along with the 17 other units on campus, contributes to the funding of the center.
    Another interesting topic covered in the files is the re-location of the Lorch Column. Originally located in the courtyard of Lorch Hall (the original home of the College of Architecture), the column was moved to the front of the Art and Architecture Building on North Campus. The column was restored to its original height using a steel insert, and renamed the Lorch Column in honor of Emil Lorch, founder of the College of Architecture. The dedication of the column in October 2007 consummated the College's centennial, celebrated in 2006. It may also be of interest to note that initially the column was to be re-located along with an entry portal that also stood near Lorch Hall on Central Campus. However, the entry portal was left standing in the lawn just southwest of Lorch Hall. The files included proposals to move both the column and the portal, along with enhanced photographs of proposed sites for the two sculptures. (See also oversize materials relating to the relocation of the column in Box 59).
    The files also contain information on A. Alfred Taubman's involvement with and interest in the College of Architecture. A file titled "Taubman Building Project" contains documentation on an attempt to expand and renovate the Art and Architecture Building. This project was to be funded with assistance from Taubman, but prohibitive costs prevented the renovation from moving forward (for further documentation on the renovation project refer to another series in this accession: Art and Architecture Building Renovation). However, Taubman remained in contact with the college, and shortly after the building project fell through, discussion began around the possibility of establishing an endowment for the school. The "Taubman Proposal" file includes correspondence and drafts of proposals regarding the $30 million gift from Taubman to establish the endowment. Following the donation, the College of Architecture and Urban Planning was renamed in Taubman's honor.
    - 1993-2008 1998-2008
      - Advisory Committee on Public Art 2006-2008 (Box 56)
      - Architecture Program 2001-2007 (Box 56)
        (scattered, includes accreditation materials from the NAAB)
      - Art and Architecture Building
        (see also oversized Box 59)
        - Improvements/Updates 1999-2007 (scattered) (Box 56)
        - Media Center and First Floor Classroom Renovations 2002-2005 (Box 56)
        - Missions and Visions: Next Steps 2000 (Box 56)
        - Space Report 2001-2003 (Box 56)
      - Art and Design, School of (SOAD) 1998-2003 (Box 56)
      - Arts on Earth (AoE) 2007-2008 (Box 56)
      - Budget Request
        - 2002 (Box 56)
        - 2003 (Box 56)
        - 2004 (Box 56)
        - 2005 (Box 56)
        - 2006 (Box 56)
        - 2007 (Box 56)
        - 2008 (Box 56)
        - 2009 (Box 56)
      - Building Expansion Preliminary Funding and Design Proposal 2007-2009 (Box 56)
      - Campus Plan Advisory Committee 1998-2002 (Box 56)
      - Centennial/100th Anniversary 2004-2007 (Box 56)
        (college centennial celebrated in 2006)
      - Centennial Conferences
        - Global Place: Politics, Practice, and the Polis 2005-2007 (Box 56)
        - Rewind/Pause/Fast Forward 2006 (Box 56)
      - Charrettes
        - Cass Corridor 1999 (Box 56)
        - Michigan at Trumbull 2000 (Box 56)
        - Grand River Avenue 2001 (Box 56)
        - Detroit Downtown 2002 (Box 56)
        - Reflecting the Riverfront 2003 (Box 56)
        - West Riverfront 2004 (Box 56)
        - Eastern Market and Beyond 2005 (Box 56)
        - Aerotropolis 2006 (Box 56)
        - 5-D: Adding Three Dimensions to Downtown Detroit 2007 (Box 56)
        - Troy/Birmingham Transit Center 2008, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 56)
          (includes CD containing an introduction to the charrette, and identifying each team and their project)
      - Chicago Visit June 1995 (Box 57)
      - China Trip 2003 (Box 57)
      - Chinese Visitors May 2006 (Box 57)
      - Coleman, Mary Sue -- University President 2002 (Box 57)
      - College Rules (correspondence and notes) 1995-2004 (scattered) (Box 57)
      - Detroit Center
        - General
          - 1999-2002 (Box 57)
          - 2002-2004 (Box 57)
          - 2004-2005 (Box 57)
          - 2005-2006 (Box 57)
          - 2006-2007 (Box 57)
        - Construction 2005 (Box 57)
        - Detroit Community Design Center 2005-2007 (Box 57)
        - Information Booklet and Brochure 2006-2007 (Box 57)
      - Developers Dinner with Ken Greenberg November 1994 (Box 57)
      - Diversity (post-Proposal 2) 2004-2007 (Box 57)
      - Doctoral Program in Architecture 1999-2007 (scattered) (Box 57)
      - Faculty and Staff Awards Dinner
        - 1998 (Box 57)
        - 2001 (Box 57)
        - 2002 (Box 57)
      - Faculty Retreat
        - June 1995 (Box 57)
        - December 1998 (Box 57)
      - Faculty Retreats 1995-2006 (scattered) (Box 57)
      - Grand Rapids Reception March 1993 (Box 57)
      - India Program 1998-2005 (Box 57)
      - International Programs 2005-2006 (Box 57)
      - Lafayette Park Design Competition (a.k.a. Mies Competition) 2004 (Box 57)
      - Lectures and Exhibits 1999-2004 (Box 57)
      - Lorch Column and Portal Relocation Project
        - General
          - 1999 (Box 57)
          - 2006 (Box 57)
        - Photographs: Possible Re-location Sites 1999, 2006 (Box 57)
      - Lorch Column Design and Construction 2006-2007, 2 folders (Box 58)
      - Methodologies of Urban Design (M.U.D.) 2004-2008 (scattered) (Box 58)
      - Murcutt, Glenn -- dinner April 2003 (Box 58)
      - Museum of Art (UMMA) Executive Committee 2002-2009 (scattered) (Box 58)
      - National Council of Architectural Registration Boards (NCARB) Conference June 1994 (Box 58)
      - Natural Resources and Environment, School of (SNRE) Projects 1999-2007 (Box 58)
      - New Urbanism Conference 2000-2001 (Box 58)
      - North Campus Deans 2003-2008 (Box 58)
      - North Campus Planning Committee 2005-2007 (Box 58)
      - North Campus Redux 2002 (Box 58)
      - North Campus Symposium October 1996 (Box 58)
      - Planning Advisory Committee (PAC) 2003-2005 (Box 58)
      - Real Estate Forum
        - November 1996 (Box 58)
        - November 1998 (Box 58)
        - November 2003 (Box 58)
      - Report on the Task Force on GSI and Supplemental Faculty March 2001 (Box 58)
      - Reports to Faculty, Students, and Staff 1999-2001, 2007 (Box 58)
      - Research 2002-2007 (Box 58)
        (scattered, includes "Report on the State of Research in the College" from July 25, 2007)
      - Sustainable Mobility
        - From Mobility to Accessibility: A Symposium and Workshop on Sustainable Transportation 2004 (Box 58)
        - Mobility in a Sustainable World: A Complex Systems Approach 2003-2004 (Box 58)
      - Taubman Building Project 1998-1999 (Box 58)
      - Taubman Proposal 1999 (Box 58)
      - University Architect's Office 1999-2001 (Box 58)
      - Urban and Regional Planning (URP) 2001-2004 (Box 58)
      - WorkPlay Design Competition ("The Grove") 2007-2008 (Box 58)
      - Art and Architecture Building Addition Pre-Design Document May 29, 2007 (Box 59)
      - Lorch Column and Portal Relocation Project Plans circa 2005 (Box 59)
  - Herbert W. Johe
    Papers of Assistant Dean Herbert Johe, who was appointed in 1959, are also contained include material on the Centennial Event in 1976; correspondence relating to the architectural fragments belonging to the college; correspondence pertaining to the six-year degree program, and two surveys of architecture students taken in 1972 and 1975, the first at Michigan and the second at Princeton University.
    - 1972-1976
      - Centennial Event 1976 (Box 4)
      - Fragments, Architectural 1972-1974 (Box 4)
      - Six-year Architecture Degree Program 1966-1971 (Box 4)
      - Surveys
        - Architectural Record (classes of, 1965, 1967, 1969, 1972 (Box 4)
        - Princeton University 1975 (Box 4)
- National Architectural Accrediting Board 1955-1989
  The National Architectural Accrediting Board series includes reports or portions of reports for 1955 to 1961, 1965-1966, 1970-1971, 1976, 1981 1987, 1988, 1993, and 1998, along with correspondence and other related material for 1981-1982 and 1986-1989. Much can be gleaned from these records, since the National Architectural Accrediting Board requires a self-assessment statement and description of its programs, followed by a site visit and an evaluation report. This is substantial documentation, from organization, governance, programming and recruitment of staff to physical facilities and public service. Appendices to reports include faculty profiles, course descriptions, and statistical data.
  - 1951-1981
    - Correspondence 1951 (Box 4)
    - School Evaluation Reports
      - 1955-1960 (Box 4)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - 1976 (Box 4)
      - 1981 (Box 4)
  - 1988-1993
    - Architecture Program Report 1988 (Box 47)
    - Architecture Program Report 1993 Supplement, and Draft Site Visit Report (Box 47)
    - Architecture Program Report 1998 (Box 47)
    - Final Application, Planning Degree Initial Accreditation, Volume II Appendices 1987 (Box 47)
    - Re-Accreditation Self-Study Report, 1997-98 (Box 47)
    - Related Files
      - 1981-1982 (Box 47)
      - 1986-1987
      - 1987-1988 (Box 47)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 47)
  - 1987-1998
    - Strategic Planning, Volumes 1-5 1987 (Box 54)
    - 1994, 2 folders (Box 54)
    - 1998 Program Report (Box 54)
    - Correspondence 1994-1997 (Box 54)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series contains material on Jacques Brownson, an architecture department chairman; a 1971 exhibit by Konrad Wachsmann; and miscellaneous correspondence.
  - Brownson, Jacques (Box 4)
  - Wachsmann, Konrad (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 4)
- Raoul G. Wallenberg